we seem to be heading into something of
a meaning crisis in our society so this
is work I do with Christopher master
master Pietro and what we what we're
doing in a book were writing called
science and the sages we talk about what
we call the zombie zeitgeist that what's
going on right now is we've got this
proliferation of the presentation and
stories and movies and TV shows about
zombies so you have the Walking Dead
we've got a movie right now doing a riff
on Romeo and Juliet involving zombies
we've got World War Z coming which is
about zombies and then you know Dawn of
the Dead and Shaun of the Dead and we've
just got a proliferation and we actually
track this and there's been sort of this
exponential increase and all of this
presentation but it's not just
presentation people want to be they want
to participate they want to be involved
on it we have sort of zombie happenings
people you know will suddenly you know
dress up as zombies and and take on the
the mannerisms of zombies there's you
know there was a discussion just in the
Canadian Parliament about whether or not
we should sort of use zombies to put to
prepare ourselves for particular
emergency situations now there's a
humorous aspect to this but there's also
a deeply serious point and the deeply
serious point is this culture is zeroing
in on a mythology a mythic
representation that is trying to give
expression trying to articulate
something that is going profoundly wrong
we're trying to create an image we're
trying to create a narrative we're
trying to give right speech and picture
to something that is very pervasive very
profound but very hard to articulate and
this is what Chris and I call the the
growing meaning crisis because the
zombie represents a loss of meaning
think about all the weird features about
a zombie okay so first of all zombies
right have lost most of the capacity for
meaning they can't speak anymore they
can't generate meaning they've dropped
down to this very very basic level of
just wanting to eat and consume what's
really odd is they they're it's this
kind of a hole because they want to eat
the very organ that typically creates
meaning they want to eat brains so they
represent this fundamental loss of
meaning but the way they move they drift
they drift around they represent again
one of our pervasive metaphors for
finding our lives meaningless that we're
adrift we're wandering aimlessly we
don't know where we're going we don't
have a purpose notice also that zombies
unlike you know Dracula or Frankenstein
not only lacking in home but incapable
of having a home and that again is a way
in which people often express a sense of
meaninglessness I have no home I don't
belong there's nowhere I should be but
think about the weird other features
about his arm zombies don't have any
supernatural powers other than coming
back from life coming back from the dead
right they don't represent any important
intervention from supernatural forces or
divine agencies they're just this
catastrophic failure that is being
inflicted on the struggling remnants of
humanity and they have this weird again
twist in them the zombie is the only
communal monster you don't get usually
packs of vampires right you know but but
the zombies hang out in herds it's like
they almost have community but they
represent in fact that they can't
actually enter into community they long
the way they they in some sense
represent the longing we have to belong
to each other they represent a loss of
how we belong to ourselves
zombies unlike vampires or other right
monsters zombies lack self-awareness by
definition it's one of the fundamental
things a zombie in no way belongs to him
or herself
they've lost this in a profound way and
even the narrative around the zombie
points to the meaning crisis usually
what's going on right in a supernatural
story is there some answer or solution
to the problem or if it's even if it's a
tragedy like you know the tragedy of
Odysseus or something or the tragedy not
the tragedy of Odysseus but the tragedy
of Orpheus or the tragedy to piss wrecks
right we know what's going on we have
the answer but when we're watching a
zombie movie right that's missing
there's no there's no answer to the
proper yeah you could kill some zombies
but then what and we know that it you
know there's an inevitable it's going to
get worse and worse but we don't have
any answer either as to what should be
done I mean the answer is you know to
create a meaningful civilization that's
the actual response in a zombie
situation but we don't know what that is
we don't know what to do we're no better
off and so it's not a tragedy it's not
like we have an insight into what the
hero should be doing instead we sit
there and we go through the zombie
apocalypse but we're no better off than
the people suffering in the film and
there's a weird sort of there's a weird
sort of take in the genre that points to
the fact that you know there's this lack
of self-awareness there's the the lack
of our superiority because one of the
weird things is it's one of the standard
tropes of the zombie genre is that
nobody uses the word zombie to describe
the monsters in the movies now there's
some variation on it but in almost all
the films you don't call thumbs up
they're called the walkers or they're
called this or they're called that
because that's a reflection of the fact
that we right really don't have right
any kind of participatory superiority
over the poor folks that are in the
zombie apocalypse yeah we know they're
called the zombie they never say that
and that's a way of saying like we can't
offer them anything we can't help them
it's useless we have this profound
symbol that's becoming pervasive and
almost magnetic in its attractiveness
for the fact that our culture is facing
a profound crisis of meaning the way we
are connected to ourself the way we're
connected to each other the way we're
connected to the universe and find it a
home that we belong to
all of this has been seriously
undermined and lost and we don't know
how to address this meaning crisis now
what I want to suggest to you is that
there is an answer to this but it
involves a very different approach to
understanding what's going on in how
human brains and minds make meaning and
this would be a discussion about the
nature of wisdom and the cultivation of
compassion but that's another talk